<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Monad on Facile.it Engineering</title>
    <link>http://engineering.facile.it/categories/monad/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Monad on Facile.it Engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://engineering.facile.it/categories/monad/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Optionals in Objective-C</title>
      <link>http://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/optionals-in-objective-c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/optionals-in-objective-c/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective-C is not going anywhere&lt;/strong&gt;. While Swift is most certainly the new hotness for iOS and OS X programming, there are some concrete reasons to stick with Objective-C for a while:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Objective-C based projects still need maintenance and new features to be added, and mixing Swift and Objective-C, while possible, &lt;strong&gt;can be tricky&lt;/strong&gt; and possibly unconvenient, due to the dynamic nature of the latter;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swift is changing rapidly, has still some bugs and &lt;strong&gt;performance problems&lt;/strong&gt;, and still lacks some features that professionals need, while Objective-C is mature and has a strong community;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some may &lt;strong&gt;prefer a more dynamic language&lt;/strong&gt;, and Objective-C support from Apple &lt;a href=&#34;https://netguru.co/blog/objective-c-generics&#34;&gt;is still strong&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, while I naturally lean towards a more static, &lt;a href=&#34;http://engineering.facile.it/type-first-development-in-swift/&#34;&gt;type-first&lt;/a&gt; approach to programming, from time to time I like to work in a more dynamic environment, so both for preference and for business needs, I still didn&amp;rsquo;t put Objective-C completely away. But just after a few weeks of Swift I found myself missing one of the most powerful features of the language: &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/Swift/Conceptual/Swift_Programming_Language/TheBasics.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP40014097-CH5-ID330&#34;&gt;Optionals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;table-of-contents&#34;&gt;Table of contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-optional-type&#34;&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; type&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#optionals-in-swift&#34;&gt;Optionals in Swift&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#back-to-objective-c&#34;&gt;Back to Objective-C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#example-a-json-parser&#34;&gt;Example: a JSON parser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;the-optional-type&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-optional-type&#34;&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; type&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Optional is a &lt;em&gt;generic&lt;/em&gt; type, that is, a type that&amp;rsquo;s dependent  (actually, &lt;em&gt;parametric&lt;/em&gt;) on another &lt;strong&gt;subtype&lt;/strong&gt;, so whe can have, for example, a &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; or a &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: thanks to some syntactic sugar, those types are written in Swift as &lt;code&gt;String?&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Int?&lt;/code&gt;. So, what is an &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;? It&amp;rsquo;s a representation   of a value that could be there, and be of a particular subtype, or could not, therefore being &lt;strong&gt;nil&lt;/strong&gt;: by &lt;em&gt;wrapping&lt;/em&gt; the subtype into an &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, the Swift compiler knows that the value could be nil, and complain in the cases where we are using an &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; where a value that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;never&lt;/strong&gt; nil is expected. By itself, this simple feature grants us a lot of type-safety for free: for example, in Swift we can&amp;rsquo;t initialize a non-optional value with nil, and considering that, for the Swift&amp;rsquo;s compiler, a value cannot be used before being initialized, by saying that a value&amp;rsquo;s type is &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt; the compiler will assure us that the value will &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; be a string, no matter what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Objective-C objects can always be nil, and if we expect something not to be nil, we are forced to check for the actual existence of everything at any time. But actually, that&amp;rsquo;s not necessarily a big deal: it&amp;rsquo;s a classic &lt;strong&gt;tradeoff&lt;/strong&gt; of dynamic languages, and it can be even considered a &lt;em&gt;feature&lt;/em&gt; by some people: in using a dynamically typed language, we are always expected to design our APIs with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Late_binding&#34;&gt;late binding&lt;/a&gt; in mind. Also, the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.apple.com/swift/blog/?id=25&#34;&gt;Objective-C nullability specifiers&lt;/a&gt; will help the compiler trigger warnings when nil is passed to a property or method parameter when &lt;code&gt;nonnull&lt;/code&gt; is expected. But the problem is still there: we need a lot of boilerplate to always check for &lt;em&gt;nullness&lt;/em&gt;, and that can produce error-prone, less readable code. The need for this boilerplate is missing in Swift, and that&amp;rsquo;s thanks to the nature of the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; type: in fact, it works in the same way as the &lt;code&gt;Maybe&lt;/code&gt; type in Haskell, or the &lt;code&gt;Option&lt;/code&gt; type in Scala, that is, &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; is actually a &lt;strong&gt;monad&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of &lt;em&gt;monad&lt;/em&gt; is inherited by functional programming from &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category_theory&#34;&gt;category theory&lt;/a&gt; and there are plenty of &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.haskell.org/Monad&#34;&gt;introductions&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.haskell.org/tutorial/monads.html&#34;&gt;about it&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://learnyouahaskell.com/a-fistful-of-monads&#34;&gt;on the web&lt;/a&gt;, so I&amp;rsquo;m not going into the specifics here: let me just say that a monad is a &lt;em&gt;computational context&lt;/em&gt;, that is, a specification for the way some &lt;em&gt;computations&lt;/em&gt; need to be resolved. Applying a certain transformation to a monad will result in another instance of the same monad, different from the first, based on the specific kind of monad. For example, applying some transformation to an &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; monad will result in applying the same transformation to the contained value if it&amp;rsquo;s there, or absolutely nothing if the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; contains nil: in both cases, the transformation&amp;rsquo;s output will be another &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, possibly of different subtype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;optionals-in-swift&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;optionals-in-swift&#34;&gt;Optionals in Swift&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following Swift code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Swift&#34;&gt;func makeOptionalIntFrom(value: Int, ifTrue: Bool) -&amp;gt; Int?
{
  return ifTrue ? value : nil
}

let optionalInt = makeOptionalIntFrom(3, ifTrue: true)
print(optionalInt.dynamicType) /// prints &#39;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&#39;

let toString: Int -&amp;gt; String = { &amp;quot;\($0)&amp;quot; }

let optionalString = optionalInt.map(toString)
print(optionalString.dynamicType) /// prints &#39;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example, &lt;code&gt;optionalInt&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;code&gt;Int&lt;/code&gt; wrapped into an &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, thus having type &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (Swift&amp;rsquo;s syntactic sugar allows us to write &lt;code&gt;Int?&lt;/code&gt;), and by applying the &lt;code&gt;toString&lt;/code&gt; function to that &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; we get an instance of &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. We can see that, to actually apply the &lt;code&gt;toString&lt;/code&gt; function to the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, we passed the function to the &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; method: this operation is usually called &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.haskell.org/Lifting&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;lifting&lt;/em&gt; a function&lt;/a&gt;, because the function &lt;code&gt;toString&lt;/code&gt;, of type &lt;code&gt;Int -&amp;gt; String&lt;/code&gt;, is &lt;em&gt;lifted&lt;/em&gt; into the type &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt; -&amp;gt; Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, no conditional statements were used in manipulating the optional integer: by &lt;em&gt;lifting&lt;/em&gt; our transformations with the &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; method, we can apply them directly to the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; instances, and we can also chain them pretty easily, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Swift&#34;&gt;func makeOptionalIntFrom(value: Int, ifTrue: Bool) -&amp;gt; Int?
{
  return ifTrue ? value : nil
}

let optionalInt = makeOptionalIntFrom(3, ifTrue: true)
print(optionalInt.dynamicType) /// prints &#39;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&#39;

let doubled: Int -&amp;gt; Int = { $0*2 }

let toString: Int -&amp;gt; String = { &amp;quot;\($0)&amp;quot; }

let optionalDoubledString = optionalInt.map(doubled).map(toString)
print(optionalDoubledString.dynamicType) /// prints &#39;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to express the opposite operation, we run into a problem: transforming a &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt; into a &lt;code&gt;Int&lt;/code&gt; is not always considered possible by Swift (for example, no numbers in the string), therefore the operation is optional. In fact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Swift&#34;&gt;func makeOptionalStringFrom(value: String, ifTrue: Bool) -&amp;gt; String?
{
  return ifTrue ? value : nil
}

let toInt: String -&amp;gt; Int? = { Int($0) }

let anotherOptionalString = makeOptionalStringFrom(&amp;quot;3&amp;quot;, ifTrue: true)

let anotherOptionalInt = anotherOptionalString.map(toInt).map(doubled)
/// this won&#39;t compile!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem here is that &lt;code&gt;toInt&lt;/code&gt; is a function of type &lt;code&gt;String -&amp;gt; Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, and lifting the function to the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ldquo;world&amp;rdquo; will turn its type into something like &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; -&amp;gt; Optional&amp;lt;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, that is, an optional integer wrapped into another optional: in &lt;em&gt;monadic&lt;/em&gt; terminology, to lift functions that transforms the wrapped type into another instance of the same monad, we need a &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; operation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Swift&#34;&gt;let anotherOptionalInt = anotherOptionalString.flatMap(toInt).map(doubled)
/// this is fine
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; type, &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; works like &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; but for functions that transform the wrapped type into another &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;. In reading the code, &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; can be basically treated as the same: they both indicate a transformation, and the fact that computations passed to &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; are of slightly different type can be considered an implementation detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, Swift treats these types &lt;strong&gt;a little differently&lt;/strong&gt; than in other languages: for example, &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; are usually &lt;em&gt;free functions&lt;/em&gt; in most &lt;em&gt;functional&lt;/em&gt; languages, while in Swift they are &lt;strong&gt;methods&lt;/strong&gt;. In general, Swift encourages the use of methods and &lt;strong&gt;method chaining&lt;/strong&gt; instead of free functions composed with special operators: it&amp;rsquo;s mostly a matter of philosophy, but in bringing these features back to Objective-C, the method-based approach is going to be really useful because there&amp;rsquo;s no easy syntax for free functions in the language, while methods have the signature clean and readable syntax that we&amp;rsquo;re used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;back-to-objective-c&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-objective-c&#34;&gt;Back to Objective-C&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s implement the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; class in Objective-C:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.h

#import &amp;lt;Foundation/Foundation.h&amp;gt;

NS_ASSUME_NONNULL_BEGIN

@interface Optional : NSObject

+ (Optional*)with:(id _Nullable)value;

- (Optional*)map:(id(^)(id))mapBlock;
- (Optional*)flatMap:(Optional*(^)(id))flatMapBlock;

@end

NS_ASSUME_NONNULL_END
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.m

#import &amp;quot;Optional.h&amp;quot;

@interface Optional ()

@property (strong, nonatomic, nullable) id value;

@end

@implementation Optional

+ (Optional*)with:(id _Nullable)value
{
  Optional* optional = [Optional new];
  optional.value = value;
  return optional;
}

- (Optional *)map:(id  _Nonnull (^)(id _Nonnull))mapBlock
{
  if (self.value != nil)
  {
    return [Optional with:mapBlock(self.value)];
  }
  return self;
}

- (Optional *)flatMap:(Optional* _Nonnull (^)(id _Nonnull))flatMapBlock
{
  if (self.value != nil)
  {
    return flatMapBlock(self.value);
  }
  return self;
}

@end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, the &lt;code&gt;with:&lt;/code&gt; class method will create an &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; object by wrapping some other object, of unspecified class: because there&amp;rsquo;s no true &lt;em&gt;generics&lt;/em&gt; in Objective-C, we won&amp;rsquo;t be able to make our Optional type as type-safe as in Swift, but as we&amp;rsquo;ll see, it won&amp;rsquo;t be a big deal and we&amp;rsquo;ll still be able to get some really &lt;strong&gt;powerful features&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;map:&lt;/code&gt; method will check if the wrapped object is not nil, and apply the transformation expressed by the &lt;code&gt;mapBlock&lt;/code&gt; block only if the object is actually there: in this case, Objective-C nullability specifiers really help us in designing our APIs, because we clearly specified that &lt;code&gt;mapBlock&lt;/code&gt; will accept and will return non-nil objects only. The &lt;code&gt;flatMapBlock&lt;/code&gt; block will return instead another &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can test this by essentially recreating the same Swift example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Test.h

#import &amp;lt;Foundation/Foundation.h&amp;gt;

@interface Test : NSObject

+ (void)testOptional;

@end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Test.m

#import &amp;quot;Test.h&amp;quot;
#import &amp;quot;Optional.h&amp;quot;

@implementation Test

+ (void)testOptional
{
  Optional* optionalInt = [self makeOptionalIntFrom:@3 ifTrue:YES];
  Optional* optionalDoubledString = [[optionalInt
                                      map:[self doubled]]
                                     map:[self toString]];
  NSLog(@&amp;quot;%@&amp;quot;, optionalDoubledString);
}

+ (Optional*)makeOptionalIntFrom:(NSNumber*)fromInt ifTrue:(BOOL)ifTrue
{
  return [Optional with:ifTrue ? fromInt : nil];
}


+ (NSNumber*(^)(NSNumber*))doubled
{
  return ^NSNumber*(NSNumber* value)  {
    return @(value.integerValue*2);
  };
}

+ (NSString*(^)(NSNumber*))toString
{
  return ^NSString*(NSNumber* value)  {
    return [NSString stringWithFormat:@&amp;quot;%@&amp;quot;, value];
  };
}

@end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we applied our transformations, we need a way to &lt;em&gt;unwrap&lt;/em&gt; the object inside our &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;: in Swift this is done at language level, with some syntactic sugar, while in Objective-C we can follow the standard conventions of the functional programming community, that is, we can &lt;em&gt;get&lt;/em&gt; the wrapped object via a &lt;code&gt;get&lt;/code&gt; method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.h

- (id _Nullable)get;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.m

- (id)get
{
  return self.value;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the &lt;code&gt;get&lt;/code&gt; method will return an &lt;code&gt;id _Nullable&lt;/code&gt;, which means that the returned object can (obviously) be nil. A frequent pattern when dealing with &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt; objects is replacing them with &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo; versions: that can be useful when we don&amp;rsquo;t really care about the data contained in an object, but we don&amp;rsquo;t want to be exposed to the risk of possibly null references. Once again, with the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; class we can avoid conditional statements and express the &amp;ldquo;defaulting&amp;rdquo; mechanism in a more declarative way: we just need to add a &lt;code&gt;getOrElse:&lt;/code&gt; method, that will return the wrapped object if it&amp;rsquo;s there, or will return a default object, that we&amp;rsquo;ll pass to the method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.h

- (id)getOrElse:(id(^)())elseBlock;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.m

- (id)getOrElse:(id  _Nonnull (^)())elseBlock
{
  if (self.value != nil)
  {
    return self.value;
  }
  return elseBlock();
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, &lt;code&gt;getOrElse:&lt;/code&gt; will &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; return a &lt;code&gt;_Nullable&lt;/code&gt; object, and that&amp;rsquo;s thanks to &lt;code&gt;elseBlock&lt;/code&gt;: we&amp;rsquo;re not passing the actual default object here, but a block that will produce one; this way, we can get the default object &lt;strong&gt;lazily&lt;/strong&gt;, because if the wrapped object is not nil, the default object doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be allocated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the rest of the article we&amp;rsquo;ll work on a more real-world example, and in doing so we&amp;rsquo;ll add more features to the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; class, making it more and more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;example-a-json-parser&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-a-json-parser&#34;&gt;Example: a JSON parser&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we want to create an app that shows movie informations: we are retrieving those informations in JSON format from a website like &lt;a href=&#34;http://api.myapifilms.com&#34;&gt;myapifilms&lt;/a&gt;. Each movie has a JSON representation like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-JSON&#34;&gt;{
    &amp;quot;countries&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;USA&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;directors&amp;quot;: [
        {
            &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Frank Darabont&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;nameId&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;nm0001104&amp;quot;
        }
    ],
    &amp;quot;filmingLocations&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;St. Croix&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;U.S. Virgin Islands&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;genres&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;Crime&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;Drama&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;idIMDB&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;tt0111161&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;languages&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;English&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;metascore&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;80/100&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;originalTitle&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;plot&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Andy Dufresne is a young and successful banker whose life changes drastically when he is convicted and sentenced to life imprisonment for the murder of his wife and her lover. Set in the 1940s, the film shows how Andy, with the help of his friend Red, the prison entrepreneur, turns out to be a most unconventional prisoner.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;ranking&amp;quot;: 1,
    &amp;quot;rated&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;R&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;rating&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;9.3&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;releaseDate&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;19941014&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;runtime&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;142 min&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;simplePlot&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Two imprisoned men bond over a number of years, finding solace and eventual redemption through acts of common decency.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;title&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;The Shawshank Redemption&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Movie&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;urlIMDB&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0111161&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;urlPoster&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;http://ia.media-imdb.com/images/M/MV5BODU4MjU4NjIwNl5BMl5BanBnXkFtZTgwMDU2MjEyMDE@._V1_SX214_AL_.jpg&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;votes&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;1,533,914&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;writers&amp;quot;: [
        {
            &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Stephen King&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;nameId&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;nm0000175&amp;quot;
        },
        {
            &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Frank Darabont&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;nameId&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;nm0001104&amp;quot;
        }
    ],
    &amp;quot;year&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;1994&amp;quot;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course we want to define our own internal representation with a value object, change some structure and ignore the parts that we consider not relevant. Here&amp;rsquo;s a possible interface for the &lt;code&gt;Movie&lt;/code&gt; class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;NS_ASSUME_NONNULL_BEGIN

@interface Movie : NSObject

@property (copy, nonatomic, readonly) NSString* title;
@property (copy, nonatomic, readonly) NSNumber* rating;
@property (copy, nonatomic, readonly) NSNumber* year;
@property (copy, nonatomic, readonly) NSNumber* lengthInMinutes;

+ (Movie*)withJSONDict:(NSDictionary*)dict;

@end

NS_ASSUME_NONNULL_END
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The class method &lt;code&gt;withJSONDict:&lt;/code&gt; will create an instance of &lt;code&gt;Movie&lt;/code&gt; from a JSON dictionary like the one showed before: as we can see from the interface declaration, we decided to not allow nil values for any of the properties; but when dealing with JSON, we must consider &lt;strong&gt;every possibility&lt;/strong&gt;, including missing keys, null values or wrong types. We&amp;rsquo;re going to use the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; type to parse the JSON dict in a clean, declarative and error-proof way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the title. From the JSON, the title should be given by the &amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo; key, and should be a string (&lt;code&gt;NSString&lt;/code&gt; in Objective-C), so we can get the title via the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt; NSString* title = [[[[Optional
                        with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;]]
                       
                       flatMap:^Optional*(id title) {
                         return [Optional with:[title isKindOfClass:[NSString class]] ? title : nil];
                       }]
                      
                      flatMap:^Optional*(NSString* title) {
                        return [Optional with:title.length &amp;gt; 0 ? title : nil];
                      }]
                     
                     getOrElse:^NSString*{
                       return @&amp;quot;NO TITLE&amp;quot;;
                     }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first &lt;code&gt;flatMap:&lt;/code&gt; step means that we want the title to be of &lt;code&gt;NSString&lt;/code&gt; class. It&amp;rsquo;s convenient to abstract this operation directly into the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; constructor, because we&amp;rsquo;re going to do it all the time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;+ (Optional *)with:(id)value as:(Class)valueClass
{
  if ([value isKindOfClass:valueClass])
  {
    return [Optional with:value];
  }
  return [Optional with:nil];
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second &lt;code&gt;flatMap:&lt;/code&gt; step means that if the found string is of length 0 (that is, empty), we are going to treat it as unknown. Actually, this step will act as a &lt;strong&gt;filter&lt;/strong&gt;, because it will only &lt;em&gt;let pass&lt;/em&gt; the strings that are not empty; with that in mind, let&amp;rsquo;s add a &lt;code&gt;filter:&lt;/code&gt; method to the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.h

- (Optional*)filter:(BOOL(^)(id))filterBlock;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.m

- (Optional*)filter:(BOOL (^)(id _Nonnull))filterBlock
{
  return [self flatMap:^Optional*(id value) {
    if (filterBlock(value))
    {
      return self;
    }
    else
    {
      return [Optional with:nil];
    }
  }];
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;filter:&lt;/code&gt; method takes as parameter a block that returns a &lt;code&gt;BOOL&lt;/code&gt; based on the wrapped value: internally, &lt;code&gt;filter:&lt;/code&gt; will actually call &lt;code&gt;flatMap:&lt;/code&gt;, with a conditional expression to check if the &lt;code&gt;filterBlock&lt;/code&gt; succeeds or fails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;NSString* title = [[[Optional
                       with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;]
                       as:[NSString class]]
                      
                      filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
                        return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
                      }]
                     
                     getOrElse:^NSString*{ return @&amp;quot;NO TITLE&amp;quot;; }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, no conditional statements, and very few lines of code, completely declarative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;code&gt;rating&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;year&lt;/code&gt; parameters we need to add a &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; to convert the &lt;code&gt;NSString&lt;/code&gt; into an &lt;code&gt;NSNumber&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;NSNumber* rating = [[[[Optional
                         with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;rating&amp;quot;]
                         as:[NSString class]]
                        
                        filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
                          return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
                        }]
                       
                       map:^NSNumber*(NSString* stringValue) {
                         return [NSDecimalNumber decimalNumberWithString:stringValue];
                       }]
                      
                      getOrElse:^NSNumber*{ return @0; }];
  movie.rating = rating;
  
  NSNumber* year = [[[[Optional
                       with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;year&amp;quot;]
                       as:[NSString class]]
                      
                      filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
                        return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
                      }]
                     
                     map:^NSNumber*(NSString* stringValue) {
                       return [NSDecimalNumber decimalNumberWithString:stringValue];
                     }]
                    
                    getOrElse:^NSNumber*{ return @0; }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;lenghtInMinutes&lt;/code&gt; parameter is a little tricky; from the JSON we can see that the value is represented like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-JSON&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;runtime&amp;quot;: [ 
	&amp;quot;142 min&amp;quot; 
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we expect an array, of which we&amp;rsquo;re only interested in the first element (thus, the array must not be empty), that has to be a string; of this string we only need the first part, removing the &lt;code&gt;min&lt;/code&gt; portion. Luckily, we already have all the tools for the job:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;  NSNumber* lengthInMinutes =
  [[[[[[Optional
        with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;runtime&amp;quot;]
        as:[NSArray class]]
       
       flatMap:^Optional*(NSArray* array) {
         return [Optional with:[array firstObject]];
       }]
      
      map:^NSString*(NSString* string) {
        return [string
                stringByReplacingOccurrencesOfString:@&amp;quot; min&amp;quot;
                withString:@&amp;quot;&amp;quot;];
      }]
     
     filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
       return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
     }]
    
    map:^NSNumber*(NSString* stringValue) {
      return @([stringValue integerValue]);
    }]
   
   getOrElse:^NSNumber*{ return @0; }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, something is missing: the method &lt;code&gt;[array firstObject]&lt;/code&gt; returns the first object of the array if the array has at least one element, or nil if the array is empty: there&amp;rsquo;s no indication that the first object is actually a &lt;code&gt;NSString&lt;/code&gt;, so we need to add a &lt;code&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; step to insure that the object is an instance of the correct class. Let&amp;rsquo;s do it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt; NSNumber* lengthInMinutes =
  [[[[[[[Optional
         with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;runtime&amp;quot;]
         as:[NSArray class]]
        
        flatMap:^id(NSArray* array) {
          return [Optional with:[array firstObject]];
        }]
       
       filter:^BOOL(id value) {
         return [value isKindOfClass:[NSString class]];
       }]
      
      map:^NSString*(NSString* string) {
        return [string
                stringByReplacingOccurrencesOfString:@&amp;quot; min&amp;quot;
                withString:@&amp;quot;&amp;quot;];
      }]
     
     filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
       return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
     }]
    
    map:^NSNumber*(NSString* stringValue) {
      return @([stringValue integerValue]);
    }]
   
   getOrElse:^NSNumber*{ return @0; }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, when we work with the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; class, adding a condition simply means &lt;strong&gt;adding a step&lt;/strong&gt; in the linear &lt;strong&gt;flow of expressions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing back the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; type from Swift to Objective-C allowed us to build a JSON parsing routine, often something hard to maintain and error-prone, in a simple, linear and readable way. Of course there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;plenty of cases&lt;/strong&gt; where working with optionals can give us the same advantages: by composing &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; operations we can express our intent in a clean and readable way. But this is not just about the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; type: some readers may have probably noticed that many languages (including Swift) allow operations with the same names on lists and arrays, and the meanings are also the same: &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt;, in particular, are &lt;strong&gt;generic concepts&lt;/strong&gt; related to monads (in fact, the array type is also a monad) and allow declarative compositions of transformations. This concept is at the core of &lt;strong&gt;functional programming&lt;/strong&gt;, and I think there&amp;rsquo;s plenty of reasons to apply similar concepts to a more object-oriented environment: they will help the programmer in reasoning about the code and express the intent in a more declarative way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for the &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; class used throughout the article can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/broomburgo/e318228a5f7d6a605e82&#34;&gt;GitHub Gist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optionals in Objective-C</title>
      <link>http://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/optionals-in-objective-c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/optionals-in-objective-c/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective-C vivrà ancora per molto&lt;/strong&gt;. Nonostante Swift sia il nuovo punto di riferimento per lo sviluppo iOS e OS X, ci sono ragioni concrete per scegliere di continuare a sviluppare in Objective-C, almeno per un po&amp;rsquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;progetti esistenti basati su Objective-C richiedono ancora mantenimento e probabile aggiunta di nuove funzionalità, e anche se è tecnicamente possibile mescolare i linguaggi, la cosa può risultare &lt;strong&gt;poco conveniente&lt;/strong&gt; per via della natura molto dinamica di Objective-C;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swift sta cambiando rapidamente, presenta ancora alcuni bug e &lt;strong&gt;problemi di performance&lt;/strong&gt;, e il suo workflow manca ancora di alcune feature fondamentali per i professionisti, mentre Objective-C è un linguaggio maturo, con una community molto vivace;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;alcuni possono &lt;strong&gt;preferire un linguaggio più dinamico&lt;/strong&gt;, e il supporto di Apple su Objective-C è &lt;a href=&#34;https://netguru.co/blog/objective-c-generics&#34;&gt;ancora forte&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personalmente ho la tendenza a preferire linguaggi più statici, e un approccio &lt;a href=&#34;http://engineering.facile.it/type-first-development-in-swift/&#34;&gt;type-first&lt;/a&gt; alla programmazione, ma di tanto in tanto mi piace lavorare in un ambiente più &lt;em&gt;dinamico&lt;/em&gt;, quindi, sia per preferenza personale che per esigenze di business, non ho ancora messo Objective-C da parte. Ma dopo poche settimane di Swift, mi è mancata subito una delle sue funzionalità più potenti: gli &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/Swift/Conceptual/Swift_Programming_Language/TheBasics.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP40014097-CH5-ID330&#34;&gt;Optionals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;indice&#34;&gt;Indice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#il-tipo-optional&#34;&gt;Il tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#optionals-in-swift&#34;&gt;Optionals in Swift&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#torniamo-a-objective-c&#34;&gt;Torniamo a Objective-C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#esempio-un-parser-json&#34;&gt;Esempio: un parser JSON&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusione&#34;&gt;Conclusione&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;il-tipo-optional&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;il-tipo-optional&#34;&gt;Il tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; è un tipo &lt;em&gt;generico&lt;/em&gt; (o, più propriamente, &lt;em&gt;parametrico&lt;/em&gt;), dipendente da un &lt;strong&gt;tipo secondario&lt;/strong&gt;: è possibile ad esempio definire un &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; oppure un &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;: la sintassi di Swift permette di scrivere i tipi appena indicati con &lt;code&gt;String?&lt;/code&gt; e &lt;code&gt;Int?&lt;/code&gt;. Ma cos&amp;rsquo;è esattamente un &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;?. È un tipo particolare che serve a rappresentare un dato che &lt;em&gt;potrebbe&lt;/em&gt; esistere, ed essere quindi di un certo tipo secondario, o potrebbe non esistere, ed essere quindi &lt;strong&gt;nil&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;inscatolando&lt;/em&gt; il valore opzionale in un &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, il compilatore di Swift saprà che quel valore potrà essere nil, e emettere un errore nei casi in cui stiamo usando un &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; dove ci si aspetta un valore &lt;strong&gt;sempre&lt;/strong&gt; presente. Questa semplice funzionalità ci garantisce notevole rigore nella definizione dei nostri tipi di dato e funzione: ad esempio, in Swift non possiamo inizializzare un valore non opzionale con nil, e considerando che, per il compilatore, un valore non può essere usato prima di essere istanziato, se assegniamo il tipo &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt; a un valore, siamo sicuri al 100% che quel valore sarà &lt;strong&gt;sempre a comunque&lt;/strong&gt; una stringa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al contrario, in Objective-C un oggetto può essere sempre nil, e spesso siamo costretti a controllare l&amp;rsquo;effettiva presenza di un oggetto ogni volta in cui abbiamo bisogno di un&amp;rsquo;istanza che non sia nil. In realtà non si tratta di un grosso problema: è un classico &lt;strong&gt;compromesso&lt;/strong&gt; dei linguaggi dinamici, e il fatto che posso sempre inviare un messaggio a un riferimento nil può essere anche considerato una &lt;em&gt;feature&lt;/em&gt;: usando un linguaggio dinamico, ci si aspetta che progettiamo le nostre API tenendo sempre in considerazione il concetto di &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Late_binding&#34;&gt;late-binding&lt;/a&gt;. Inoltre, i nuovi &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.apple.com/swift/blog/?id=25&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;nullability specifiers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; di Objective-C aiutano il compilatore a emettere avvisi quando stiamo passando nil a un metodo o una &lt;em&gt;property&lt;/em&gt; che richiedono invece che il parametro sia &lt;code&gt;nonnull&lt;/code&gt;. Ma il problema rimane: abbiamo bisogno di molto &lt;em&gt;boilerplate&lt;/em&gt; per verificare se qualcosa è nil, e ciò può portare a codice poco leggibile e comprensibile, soggetto ad errori. Swift non ha tipicamente bisogno di questo &lt;em&gt;boilerplate&lt;/em&gt; grazie alla natura stessa del tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;: esso ha le stesse caratteristiche del tipo &lt;code&gt;Maybe&lt;/code&gt; in Haskell, o del tipo &lt;code&gt;Option&lt;/code&gt; in Scala, cioè &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; è in realtà un &lt;strong&gt;monad&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il concetto di &lt;em&gt;monad&lt;/em&gt; è ereditato, in programmazione funzionale, dalla &lt;a href=&#34;https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teoria_delle_categorie&#34;&gt;teoria delle categorie&lt;/a&gt;, ed è facile trovare &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.haskell.org/Monad&#34;&gt;molti&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.haskell.org/tutorial/monads.html&#34;&gt;testi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://learnyouahaskell.com/a-fistful-of-monads&#34;&gt;introduttivi&lt;/a&gt; sul tema, quindi non approfondirò ulteriormente: dirò solo che un &lt;em&gt;monad&lt;/em&gt; è un &lt;em&gt;contesto computazionale&lt;/em&gt;, quindi una &lt;em&gt;specifica&lt;/em&gt; per il modo in cui una espressione deve essere valutata. Applicare una certa trasformazione a un &lt;em&gt;monad&lt;/em&gt; avrà come risultato un&amp;rsquo;altra istanza dello stesso &lt;em&gt;monad&lt;/em&gt; differente dalla prima, a seconda dello specifico tipo di &lt;em&gt;monad&lt;/em&gt;. Ad esempio, applicare una trasformazione a un &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; risulterà nell&amp;rsquo;applicazione della stessa trasformazione al valore &lt;em&gt;contenuto&lt;/em&gt;, se presente, o assolutamente niente se l&amp;rsquo;&lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; contiene nil: in entrambi i casi, il risultato della trasformazione sarà un nuovo &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, possibilmente con un tipo secondario diverso.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;optionals-in-swift&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;optionals-in-swift&#34;&gt;Optionals in Swift&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consideriamo il seguente codice Swift:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Swift&#34;&gt;func makeOptionalIntFrom(value: Int, ifTrue: Bool) -&amp;gt; Int?  
{
  return ifTrue ? value : nil
}

let optionalInt = makeOptionalIntFrom(3, ifTrue: true)  
print(optionalInt.dynamicType) /// prints &#39;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&#39;

let toString: Int -&amp;gt; String = { &amp;quot;\($0)&amp;quot; }

let optionalString = optionalInt.map(toString)  
print(optionalString.dynamicType) /// prints &#39;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nell&amp;rsquo;esempio, &lt;code&gt;optionalInt&lt;/code&gt; è un &lt;code&gt;Int&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;contenuto&lt;/em&gt; in un &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, che quindi ha tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (in Swift è possibile abbreviarlo in &lt;code&gt;Int?&lt;/code&gt;), e applicando ad esso la funzione &lt;code&gt;toString&lt;/code&gt; otteniamo un&amp;rsquo;istanza di &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Possiamo vedere che, per applicare effettivamente la funzione &lt;code&gt;toString&lt;/code&gt;, abbiamo passato la funzione come argomento al metodo &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; del &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;: questa operazione è solitamente chiamata &lt;em&gt;lifting&lt;/em&gt; di una funzione, perché la funzione &lt;code&gt;toString&lt;/code&gt;, di tipo &lt;code&gt;Int -&amp;gt; String&lt;/code&gt;, è &lt;em&gt;sollevata&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;lifted&lt;/em&gt;) fino a diventare di tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt; -&amp;gt; Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come possiamo vedere, non sono state usate istruzioni condizionali nel manipolare il valore intero &lt;em&gt;opzionale&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;sollevando&lt;/em&gt; le trasformazioni con il metodo &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;, possiamo applicarle direttamente alle istanze di &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, e possiamo anche concatenarle molto facilmente, ad esempio:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Swift&#34;&gt;func makeOptionalIntFrom(value: Int, ifTrue: Bool) -&amp;gt; Int?  
{
  return ifTrue ? value : nil
}

let optionalInt = makeOptionalIntFrom(3, ifTrue: true)  
print(optionalInt.dynamicType) /// prints &#39;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&#39;

let doubled: Int -&amp;gt; Int = { $0*2 }

let toString: Int -&amp;gt; String = { &amp;quot;\($0)&amp;quot; }

let optionalDoubledString = optionalInt.map(doubled).map(toString)  
print(optionalDoubledString.dynamicType) /// prints &#39;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volendo esprimere l&amp;rsquo;operazione opposta, avremmo un problema: trasformare una stringa in un intero non è sempre possibile in Swift (ad esempio se non c&amp;rsquo;è alcun numero nella stringa), quindi l&amp;rsquo;operazione stessa risulterebbe in un &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;. Infatti:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Swift&#34;&gt;func makeOptionalStringFrom(value: String, ifTrue: Bool) -&amp;gt; String?  
{
  return ifTrue ? value : nil
}

let toInt: String -&amp;gt; Int? = { Int($0) }

let anotherOptionalString = makeOptionalStringFrom(&amp;quot;3&amp;quot;, ifTrue: true)

let anotherOptionalInt = anotherOptionalString.map(toInt).map(doubled)
/// errore di compilazione!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il problema qui è che la funzione &lt;code&gt;toInt&lt;/code&gt; è di tipo &lt;code&gt;String -&amp;gt; Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, e il &lt;em&gt;lifting&lt;/em&gt; della funzione verso il &lt;em&gt;mondo opzionale&lt;/em&gt; la trasformerebbe in una funzione del tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; -&amp;gt; Optional&amp;lt;Optional&amp;lt;Int&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, quindi un intero opzionale contenuto in un altro &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;; in base alla terminologia accettata, abbiamo bisogno di un&amp;rsquo;operazione di &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Swift&#34;&gt;let anotherOptionalInt = anotherOptionalString.flatMap(toInt).map(doubled)  
/// funziona
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quindi, per quanto riguarda il tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; è simile a &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;, ma deve essere usato per il &lt;em&gt;lifting&lt;/em&gt; di funzioni che generano altri valori opzionali. Nel leggere il codice, &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; e &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; possono sostanzialmente essere letti nello stesso modo: indicano entrambi una trasformazione, e il fatto che le funzioni passate a &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; abbiano un tipo diverso può essere considerato un dettaglio di implementazione.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In realtà Swift tratta questi tipi di dato &lt;strong&gt;in maniera differente&lt;/strong&gt; rispetto ad altri linguaggi: ad esempio, nei linguaggi &lt;em&gt;funzionali&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; e &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; sono di norma &lt;em&gt;funzioni libere&lt;/em&gt;, mentre in Swift sono &lt;strong&gt;metodi&lt;/strong&gt;. In generale, Swift incoraggia l&amp;rsquo;uso dei metodi, e del loro &lt;strong&gt;concatenamento&lt;/strong&gt;, invece di funzioni libere, composte con operatori speciali: si tratta, più che altro, di una questione filosofica, ma nel trasportare queste feature in Objective-C l&amp;rsquo;approccio basato sui metodi tornerà utile poiché non c&amp;rsquo;è un modo semplice di rappresentare funzioni libere nel linguaggio, mentre i metodi hanno la classica sintassi alla quale siamo abituati.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;torniamo-a-objective-c&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;torniamo-a-objective-c&#34;&gt;Torniamo a Objective-C&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implementiamo la classe &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; in Objective-C:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.h

#import &amp;lt;Foundation/Foundation.h&amp;gt;

NS_ASSUME_NONNULL_BEGIN

@interface Optional : NSObject

+ (Optional*)with:(id _Nullable)value;

- (Optional*)map:(id(^)(id))mapBlock;
- (Optional*)flatMap:(Optional*(^)(id))flatMapBlock;

@end

NS_ASSUME_NONNULL_END 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.m

#import &amp;quot;Optional.h&amp;quot;

@interface Optional ()

@property (strong, nonatomic, nullable) id value;

@end

@implementation Optional

+ (Optional*)with:(id _Nullable)value
{
  Optional* optional = [Optional new];
  optional.value = value;
  return optional;
}

- (Optional *)map:(id  _Nonnull (^)(id _Nonnull))mapBlock
{
  if (self.value != nil)
  {
    return [Optional with:mapBlock(self.value)];
  }
  return self;
}

- (Optional *)flatMap:(Optional* _Nonnull (^)(id _Nonnull))flatMapBlock
{
  if (self.value != nil)
  {
    return flatMapBlock(self.value);
  }
  return self;
}

@end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come possiamo vedere, il metodo di classe &lt;code&gt;with:&lt;/code&gt; crea un oggetto &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; inscatolando un altro oggetto, di tipo non specificato: poiché non esiste un vero concetto di &lt;em&gt;generic&lt;/em&gt; in Objective-C, non sarà possibile realizzare un tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; sicuro, dal punto di vista dei tipi, come in Swift, ma non sarà un grosso problema, e saremo comunque in grado di ereditare da Swift &lt;strong&gt;potenti features&lt;/strong&gt;. Il metodo &lt;code&gt;map:&lt;/code&gt; verifica se l&amp;rsquo;oggetto contenuto non sia nil, e in tal caso applica la trasformazione espressa con &lt;code&gt;mapBlock&lt;/code&gt;: in questo caso i &lt;em&gt;nullability specifiers&lt;/em&gt; di Objective-C ci hanno aiutato nello scrivere la firma dei metodi, infatti abbiamo chiaramente specificato che &lt;code&gt;mapBlock&lt;/code&gt; accetta e ritorna oggetti che non siano nil; &lt;code&gt;flatMapBlock&lt;/code&gt; ritorna invece un altro &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possiamo testare la cosa riscrivendo lo stesso esempio visto per Swift:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Test.h

#import &amp;lt;Foundation/Foundation.h&amp;gt;

@interface Test : NSObject

+ (void)testOptional;

@end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Test.m

#import &amp;quot;Test.h&amp;quot;
#import &amp;quot;Optional.h&amp;quot;

@implementation Test

+ (void)testOptional
{
  Optional* optionalInt = [self makeOptionalIntFrom:@3 ifTrue:YES];
  Optional* optionalDoubledString = [[optionalInt
                                      map:[self doubled]]
                                     map:[self toString]];
  NSLog(@&amp;quot;%@&amp;quot;, optionalDoubledString);
}

+ (Optional*)makeOptionalIntFrom:(NSNumber*)fromInt ifTrue:(BOOL)ifTrue
{
  return [Optional with:ifTrue ? fromInt : nil];
}


+ (NSNumber*(^)(NSNumber*))doubled
{
  return ^NSNumber*(NSNumber* value)  {
    return @(value.integerValue*2);
  };
}

+ (NSString*(^)(NSNumber*))toString
{
  return ^NSString*(NSNumber* value)  {
    return [NSString stringWithFormat:@&amp;quot;%@&amp;quot;, value];
  };
}

@end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Un volta applicate le trasformazioni, abbiamo bisogno di un metodo per &amp;ldquo;estrarre&amp;rdquo; l&amp;rsquo;oggetto all&amp;rsquo;interno del &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;: Swift permette questa operazione a livello di sintassi, mentre in Objective-C possiamo seguire le convenzioni standard in programmazione funzionale, e cioè definire un metodo &lt;code&gt;get&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.h

- (id _Nullable)get;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.m

- (id)get
{
  return self.value;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il metodo &lt;code&gt;get&lt;/code&gt; ritorna un &lt;code&gt;id _Nullable&lt;/code&gt;: ciò vuol dire che l&amp;rsquo;oggetto ritornato può (ovviamente) essere nil. Un pattern frequente quando si ha a che fare con oggetti nil consiste nel sostituirli con versioni di &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo;: può essere utile quando non ci interessano tanto i dati contenuti in un oggetto, ma non vogliamo correre i rischi associati al lavorare riferimenti &lt;em&gt;null&lt;/em&gt;. Ancora una volta, con la classe &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; possiamo evitare istruzioni condizionali ed esprimere il meccanismo di &amp;ldquo;defaulting&amp;rdquo; in un modo più dichiarativo: dobbiamo semplicemente aggiungere un metodo &lt;code&gt;getOrElse:&lt;/code&gt;, che ritorni l&amp;rsquo;oggetto contenuto se presente, o un oggetto di default passato al metodo stesso:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.h

- (id)getOrElse:(id(^)())elseBlock;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.m

- (id)getOrElse:(id  _Nonnull (^)())elseBlock
{
  if (self.value != nil)
  {
    return self.value;
  }
  return elseBlock();
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come si può vedere, il metodo &lt;code&gt;getOrElse:&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;non&lt;/strong&gt; ritorna un oggetto &lt;code&gt;_Nullable&lt;/code&gt;: in effetti non stiamo passando l&amp;rsquo;oggetto, ma un block che &amp;ldquo;produrrà&amp;rdquo; l&amp;rsquo;oggetto una volta invocato; in questo modo riusciamo a ottenere l&amp;rsquo;oggetto di default in maniera &lt;strong&gt;lazy&lt;/strong&gt;, perché se l&amp;rsquo;oggetto contenuto è presente, non è necessario generare l&amp;rsquo;oggetto di default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per il resto dell&amp;rsquo;articolo lavoreremo su un esempio più concreto, e implementeremo diverse funzionalità per la classe &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, rendendola via via più utile e potente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;esempio-un-parser-json&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;esempio-un-parser-json&#34;&gt;Esempio: un parser JSON&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supponiamo di voler realizzare un&amp;rsquo;app che mostra informazioni sui film: possiamo ottenerle in formato JSON da un sito come &lt;a href=&#34;http://api.myapifilms.com/index.do&#34;&gt;myapifilms&lt;/a&gt;. La rappresentazione JSON di ogni film è del tipo seguente:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-JSON&#34;&gt;{
    &amp;quot;countries&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;USA&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;directors&amp;quot;: [
        {
            &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Frank Darabont&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;nameId&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;nm0001104&amp;quot;
        }
    ],
    &amp;quot;filmingLocations&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;St. Croix&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;U.S. Virgin Islands&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;genres&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;Crime&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;Drama&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;idIMDB&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;tt0111161&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;languages&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;English&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;metascore&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;80/100&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;originalTitle&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;plot&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Andy Dufresne is a young and successful banker whose life changes drastically when he is convicted and sentenced to life imprisonment for the murder of his wife and her lover. Set in the 1940s, the film shows how Andy, with the help of his friend Red, the prison entrepreneur, turns out to be a most unconventional prisoner.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;ranking&amp;quot;: 1,
    &amp;quot;rated&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;R&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;rating&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;9.3&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;releaseDate&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;19941014&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;runtime&amp;quot;: [
        &amp;quot;142 min&amp;quot;
    ],
    &amp;quot;simplePlot&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Two imprisoned men bond over a number of years, finding solace and eventual redemption through acts of common decency.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;title&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;The Shawshank Redemption&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Movie&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;urlIMDB&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0111161&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;urlPoster&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;http://ia.media-imdb.com/images/M/MV5BODU4MjU4NjIwNl5BMl5BanBnXkFtZTgwMDU2MjEyMDE@._V1_SX214_AL_.jpg&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;votes&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;1,533,914&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;writers&amp;quot;: [
        {
            &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Stephen King&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;nameId&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;nm0000175&amp;quot;
        },
        {
            &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Frank Darabont&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;nameId&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;nm0001104&amp;quot;
        }
    ],
    &amp;quot;year&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;1994&amp;quot;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vogliamo definire la nostra rappresentazione interna del film con un &lt;em&gt;value object&lt;/em&gt;, modificare in parte la struttura e magari ignorare alcuni elementi che non consideriamo rilevanti. Ecco un&amp;rsquo;interfaccia possibile per la classe &lt;code&gt;Movie&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;NS_ASSUME_NONNULL_BEGIN

@interface Movie : NSObject

@property (copy, nonatomic, readonly) NSString* title;
@property (copy, nonatomic, readonly) NSNumber* rating;
@property (copy, nonatomic, readonly) NSNumber* year;
@property (copy, nonatomic, readonly) NSNumber* lengthInMinutes;

+ (Movie*)withJSONDict:(NSDictionary*)dict;

@end

NS_ASSUME_NONNULL_END
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il metodo di classe &lt;code&gt;withJSONDict:&lt;/code&gt; crea un&amp;rsquo;istanza di &lt;code&gt;Movie&lt;/code&gt; da un dizionario JSON come quello appena mostrato: come si può vedere dall&amp;rsquo;interfaccia dichiarata, abbiamo deciso di non permettere valori nil per le varie &lt;em&gt;property&lt;/em&gt;; ma quando abbiamo a che fare con JSON &lt;strong&gt;tutto può succedere&lt;/strong&gt;, come chiavi mancanti, valori null o di tipo diverso. Useremo il tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; per parsare il dizionario JSON in modo chiaro, dichiarativo e a prova di errore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iniziamo con i titolo. Dal JSON vediamo che il titolo si trova in corrispondenza della chiave &amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo;, e dovrebbe essere una stringa (&lt;code&gt;NSString&lt;/code&gt; in Objective-C), quindi possiamo ottenere il titolo così:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;NSString* title = [[[[Optional
                        with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;]]

                       flatMap:^Optional*(id title) {
                         return [Optional with:[title isKindOfClass:[NSString class]] ? title : nil];
                       }]

                      flatMap:^Optional*(NSString* title) {
                        return [Optional with:title.length &amp;gt; 0 ? title : nil];
                      }]

                     getOrElse:^NSString*{
                       return @&amp;quot;NO TITLE&amp;quot;;
                     }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il primo &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; indica che l&amp;rsquo;oggetto &amp;ldquo;titolo&amp;rdquo; deve appartenere alla classe &lt;code&gt;NSString&lt;/code&gt;. Conviene astrarre questa operazione inserendola direttamente nel costruttore, perché l&amp;rsquo;applicheremo ogni volta per tutti i dati:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;+ (Optional *)with:(id)value as:(Class)valueClass
{
  if ([value isKindOfClass:valueClass])
  {
    return [Optional with:value];
  }
  return [Optional with:nil];
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il secondo &lt;code&gt;flatMap:&lt;/code&gt; indica che se la stringa trovata ha lunghezza 0, considereremo il titolo come &amp;ldquo;sconosciuto&amp;rdquo;. In effetti questo step avrà l&amp;rsquo;effetto di &amp;ldquo;filtro&amp;rdquo;, perché lascerà &amp;ldquo;passare&amp;rdquo; solo le stringhe non vuote; considerando ciò, aggiungiamo un metodo &lt;code&gt;filter:&lt;/code&gt; alla classe &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.h

- (Optional*)filter:(BOOL(^)(id))filterBlock;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;///Optional.m

- (Optional*)filter:(BOOL (^)(id _Nonnull))filterBlock
{
  return [self flatMap:^Optional*(id value) {
    if (filterBlock(value))
    {
      return self;
    }
    else
    {
      return [Optional with:nil];
    }
  }];
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il metodo &lt;code&gt;filter:&lt;/code&gt; accetta come parametro un block che ritorna un &lt;code&gt;BOOL&lt;/code&gt; basato sul valore contenuto: internamente, &lt;code&gt;filter:&lt;/code&gt; chiamerà comunque &lt;code&gt;flatMap:&lt;/code&gt;, con un&amp;rsquo;espressione condizionale che verifichi se &lt;code&gt;filterBlock&lt;/code&gt; riesce o fallisce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;NSString* title = [[[Optional  
                       with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;]
                       as:[NSString class]]

                      filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
                        return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
                      }]

                     getOrElse:^NSString*{ return @&amp;quot;NO TITLE&amp;quot;; }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quindi, nessuna espressione condizionale, e poche linee di codice, completamente dichiarative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per quanto riguarda i parametri &lt;code&gt;rating&lt;/code&gt; e &lt;code&gt;year&lt;/code&gt; abbiamo bisogno di un &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; che converta &lt;code&gt;NSString&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;NSNumber&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;NSNumber* rating = [[[[Optional  
                         with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;rating&amp;quot;]
                         as:[NSString class]]

                        filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
                          return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
                        }]

                       map:^NSNumber*(NSString* stringValue) {
                         return [NSDecimalNumber decimalNumberWithString:stringValue];
                       }]

                      getOrElse:^NSNumber*{ return @0; }];
  movie.rating = rating;

  NSNumber* year = [[[[Optional
                       with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;year&amp;quot;]
                       as:[NSString class]]

                      filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
                        return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
                      }]

                     map:^NSNumber*(NSString* stringValue) {
                       return [NSDecimalNumber decimalNumberWithString:stringValue];
                     }]

                    getOrElse:^NSNumber*{ return @0; }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il parametro &lt;code&gt;lengthInMinutes&lt;/code&gt; è un po&amp;rsquo; complicato; dal JSON possiamo vedere che la sua rappresentazione è la seguente:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-JSON&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;runtime&amp;quot;: [ 
    &amp;quot;142 min&amp;quot; 
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quindi ci aspettiamo un array, del quale siamo interessati solo al primo elemento (quindi l&amp;rsquo;array non deve essere vuoto), che deve essere una stringa; di questa stringa abbiamo bisogno solo della prima parte, rimuovendo &lt;code&gt;min&lt;/code&gt;. Fortunatamente abbiamo già tutti gli strumenti necessari per procedere:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;NSNumber* lengthInMinutes =
  [[[[[[Optional
        with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;runtime&amp;quot;]
        as:[NSArray class]]

       flatMap:^Optional*(NSArray* array) {
         return [Optional with:[array firstObject]];
       }]

      map:^NSString*(NSString* string) {
        return [string
                stringByReplacingOccurrencesOfString:@&amp;quot; min&amp;quot;
                withString:@&amp;quot;&amp;quot;];
      }]

     filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
       return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
     }]

    map:^NSNumber*(NSString* stringValue) {
      return @([stringValue integerValue]);
    }]

   getOrElse:^NSNumber*{ return @0; }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In realtà manca qualcosa: il metodo &lt;code&gt;[array firstObject]&lt;/code&gt; ritorna il primo oggetto dell&amp;rsquo;array se questo ha almeno un elemento, oppure ritorna nil se l&amp;rsquo;array è vuoto: non c&amp;rsquo;è alcuna indicazione sul fatto che vogliamo che il primo elemento sia di tipo &lt;code&gt;NSString&lt;/code&gt;, quindi dobbiamo aggiungere uno step &lt;code&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; per assicurarci che la classe dell&amp;rsquo;istanza trovata sia corretta. Quindi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ObjectiveC&#34;&gt;NSNumber* lengthInMinutes =
  [[[[[[[Optional
         with:[dict objectForKey:@&amp;quot;runtime&amp;quot;]
         as:[NSArray class]]

        flatMap:^id(NSArray* array) {
          return [Optional with:[array firstObject]];
        }]

       filter:^BOOL(id value) {
         return [value isKindOfClass:[NSString class]];
       }]

      map:^NSString*(NSString* string) {
        return [string
                stringByReplacingOccurrencesOfString:@&amp;quot; min&amp;quot;
                withString:@&amp;quot;&amp;quot;];
      }]

     filter:^BOOL(NSString* string) {
       return string.length &amp;gt; 0;
     }]

    map:^NSNumber*(NSString* stringValue) {
      return @([stringValue integerValue]);
    }]

   getOrElse:^NSNumber*{ return @0; }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come possiamo vedere, lavorando con la classe &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;, aggiungere una condizione significa semplicemente &lt;strong&gt;aggiungere uno step&lt;/strong&gt; nella sequenza lineare di espressioni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;conclusione&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusione&#34;&gt;Conclusione&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implementare la classe &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; in Objective-C ci ha permesso di parsare un JSON, cosa spesso difficile da mantenere e soggetta a errori, in un modo semplice e lineare. In realtà ci sono &lt;strong&gt;molti casi&lt;/strong&gt; in cui lavorare con gli &lt;em&gt;optionals&lt;/em&gt; ci può dare gli stessi vantaggi: componendo operazioni di tipo &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt; e &lt;code&gt;filter&lt;/code&gt; possiamo esprimere il nostro intento in maniera chiara e leggibile. Ma tutto questo non riguarda solo il tipo &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;: alcuni lettori avranno probabilmente notato che molti linguaggi (incluso Swift) permettono operazioni dell stesso tipo su liste e array, e il loro significato è identico: &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; e &lt;code&gt;flatMap&lt;/code&gt;, in particolare, sono &lt;strong&gt;concetti generici&lt;/strong&gt; legati ai &lt;em&gt;monad&lt;/em&gt; (in effetti, anche il tipo &lt;code&gt;Array&lt;/code&gt; è un &lt;em&gt;monad&lt;/em&gt;), e riguarda la composizione dichiarativa di trasformazioni. Questo concetto è alla base della &lt;strong&gt;programmazione funzionale&lt;/strong&gt;, e penso ci siano molti motivi per applicare concetti simili ad ambienti più &lt;em&gt;object-oriented&lt;/em&gt;, perché aiuterebbero il programmatore a ragionare sul codice ed esprimere l&amp;rsquo;intento in maniera più dichiarativa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il codice per la classe &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; mostrata nell&amp;rsquo;articolo è reperibile su &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/broomburgo/e318228a5f7d6a605e82&#34;&gt;GitHub Gist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>