<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Engs on Facile.it Engineering</title>
    <link>http://engineering.facile.it/eng/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Engs on Facile.it Engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://engineering.facile.it/eng/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Who we are</title>
      <link>http://engineering.facile.it/eng/who-we-are/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://engineering.facile.it/eng/who-we-are/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Questa pagina è disponibile anche in &lt;a href=&#34;http://engineering.facile.it/ita/chi-siamo&#34;&gt;italiano&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facile.it rely on a big and keen crew of developers. Since 2008, the group’s projects are based on PHP, and as time goes by new technologies become part of corporate know how.
This blog allows our developers to share tips and direct experiences with new technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facile.it is the leading price comparison website in Italy; also Assicurazione.it, Prestiti.it and Mutui.it are part of the Group. Every month we help more than 1.5 million Italians to cut their expenses, thanks to our broadband offers comparaison service. People can also save money by confronting the deals of our providers for car insurances or motorbike insurances.
Thanks to the rising trust that users put in us, we grew as a business and we can steadily provide people even better and easier ways to save money. E.g., users can simply calculate the mortgage payment or the amount of a personal loan.
Facile.it allows private consumers, companies and freelancers to find the best online deals, so it gets easier to cut the cost of gas and electricity or to save money off the phone bills thanks to home internet offers. Users can also switch their current account to a new bank, find a credit card, discount codes or vouchers, and compare car tires deals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>